<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gospel-liberty and the royal-law of love from Jesus Christ who has all power in heaven and earth given unto him, set above Axtaxerxes and Nebuchadnezer's laws and commands, and above the Medes and Persians and Darius his decrees : also several Scriptures opened ... / published for all Christian magistrates and people to read and consider, in the fear of God by G.F.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23125</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10325448</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204659</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240949014</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1831</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10325448</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1384:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gospel-liberty and the royal-law of love from Jesus Christ who has all power in heaven and earth given unto him, set above Axtaxerxes and Nebuchadnezer's laws and commands, and above the Medes and Persians and Darius his decrees : also several Scriptures opened ... / published for all Christian magistrates and people to read and consider, in the fear of God by G.F.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204659:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204659:1"/>
            <p>GOSPEL-LIBERTY, AND THE Royal-Law of Love FROM Christ Jesus, who has all Power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth given unto him, Set above <hi>Axtaxerxes and Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezer</hi>'s Laws and Commands, And above the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> and <hi>Darius</hi> his Decrees.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Also, several Scriptures opened which the Jesuits and others used to bring for Persecution, wherein their Mouthes may be stopt that plead for Persecution.</p>
               <p>And how God and Christ is Judge in his Church, Religion, Worship, and Faith: And how that it has been the Birth of the Flesh that has always persecuted him that is born of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>And also, how that Natural Affections will not destroy its own Nature; and from what ground that springs that destroys Nature.</p>
               <p>And concerning <hi>Jerusalem</hi> that is above, which is Free, with her Worshippers, and the <hi>Jerusalem</hi> that is below, that is in Bondage with her Children, whether she would bring others; with many other weighty things.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Published for all Christian Magistrates, and People, to Read and Consider, in the Fear of God. By</hi> G. F.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1668.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:204659:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:204659:2"/>
            <head>All you called Christians Consider.</head>
            <p>CHrist Jesus saith, <hi>All Power in Heaven and Earth is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to me,</hi> Math. 28. And when Christ sent Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers into a Village of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> to make ready for him, and they did not receive him; and when his Disciples <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> saw this, they said, <hi>Lord, wilt thou that we command fire to come down from Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Christ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke them that would have had fire to comedown to destroy mens-lives</note>
               <hi>and consume them, as</hi> Elias <hi>did:</hi> Mark, how Christ useth his Power to his Disciples, who were rebukable; Christ turned himself about, and rebuked them, and said, <hi>Ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of:</hi> Mark, here he lays and stops the revenge which was in the Disciples against those that would not receive him, and told them, they did not know what spirit they were of: Now, if his Disciples did not know what spirit they were of, and are under the rebuke, that would have fire to come down from Heaven to consume them that would not receive Christ; how doth all <hi>Christendom</hi> know what manner of spirits they are of, which has Prisoned, Banished, and put to Death so many about Religion? Are they not all under the rebuke of Christ, and not knowing their own spirits? For Christ, who hath all Power in Heaven and Earth, saith, That the Rebuke is to such, whose actions be done out of his Power, <hi>That the Son of Man is not come to destroy mens lives, but to save them.</hi> Now, mark, then it follows, they that destroy mens lives (and not save them) about Religion, have not the mind of Christ, neither do they act as from his Power, <hi>Who hath all Power in Heaven and Earth committed to him,</hi> Luke 9.52, 53, 54, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And also in <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.25, to vers. 30. where you may see Christ, who has all power in Heaven and Earth, useth his Power upon the forward Servants, that would be plucking up Tares, which was not their places, but the Angels: Christ's own words are as followeth, in his Parable, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is like unto a man which sowed good seed in his field; but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204659:3"/>while men slept, the Enemy came and sowed Tares among the Wheat, and went his way:</hi> (Mark, the Tares are sowed while men sleep;) <hi>When the blade sprang up, and brought forth fruit, then appeared the Tares also: So the Servant of the Housholder came, and said unto him, Sir, Didst not thou sow good seed in thy Field? From whence then hath it its Tares? He said unto them, An Enemy hath done it: The Servant said unto him▪ Wilt thou that we go and pluck them up? But he said, Nay; lest while you go to pluck up the Tares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Tares and the Wheat to grow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to pluck up the Tares, lest he shou'd pluck up the wheat also.</note>
               <hi>you root up the Wheat with them.</hi> Mark, here Christ is a Judge in the matters of Religion, who has all power in Heaven given unto him; for you may see here that he doth not give these forward Servants a Warrant to pluck up the Tares, lest they should pluck up the Wheat also; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he grant out a Warrant to pursue the Enemy that went away, after he had sown his Tares; but Christ (stops them with these words) who has all power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> saying, <hi>Let both grow till the Harvest; and in the time of Harvest I will say to the Reapers, Gather ye first the Tares, and bundle them in bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles to burn them; and gather the Wheat into my Barn.</hi> Here Christ stops these forward Servants; who saw the time that men would sleep, and then the Enemy would come, and sow his Tares; and did see also that many would be pluckers up, which was not their places, and had no commission, nor hath any commission from him to this day; and such he stops.</p>
            <p>And from the 26, verse to 42. of <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. where the Disciples came unto Christ, saying, <hi>Declare unto us the Parable of the Tares of the Field;</hi> Jesus answered, and said unto them, <hi>The Son of Man is he that soweth the good Seed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Who are the good seed, and who are the Tares.</note>
               <hi>the Field is the World; and the good Seed is the Children of the Kingdom; but the Tares are the Children of the wicked One; the Enemy that soweth them is the Devil; the Harvest is the End of the world; and the Reapers are the Angels; and the Tares are gathered to be burned in the fire. So shall it be in the end of this world, the Son of Man shall send forth his Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The world is the field in which the seeds are sown.</note>
               <hi>and they shall gather out of all Kingdoms all them that offend, and that do iniquity.</hi> Now, mark, may not Christ (who has all power in Heaven and Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) his Word stop all forward Persecutors in the whole World, (which is called the Field) where the good and the bad
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204659:3"/>Seed are sown: for, doth not he say, the Tares and the Wheat must grow till the Havest, and that is the end of the World? And doth not those that would be reaping and gathering be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the end of the World, busie themselves, and oppose Christ in his Command and Power: for seeing Christ saith, he will send forth his Angels; and when, before the Harvest? Nay: or before the End of the World? Nay: and his Angels are his Reapers; and so it is not men in the middle of the World, that must be the Reapers, and the Gatherers of the Tares;
<note place="margin">The time of Reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and who are the Reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> but it is Christ's Angels. And when then is the time of Reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? The time of Harvest, which is the end of the World: And who are the Reapers? The Angels. So then its the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels work, and not mens; so here its plain, that Christ is the Judge in matters of Religion, betwixt Tares and Wheat, who sends forth his Angels: For, mark, Christ commands men to love one another, and to love Enemies; and so, they that do not love one another, nor Enemies, doth not obey the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Christ, who hath all power in Heaven and Earth given unto him: for this is his Royal Command, <hi>Love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> by this you are known to be the Disciples of Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus; and this is the Command that Christ Jesus gave unto men and women, who has all power in Heaven and Earth, men should love one another, and Enemies; and the Angels should be Reapers; and Christ saith, <hi>Love your Enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note>
               <hi>do good to them that hate you, bless them that curse you, pray for them that dispitefully use you, and persecute you;</hi> for Christ saw that there would be Haters of his Seed, and Curses, and Dispiteful-users of it, and Persecutors of it, which would be Pluckers up of the Wheat for Tears, who had no such Command from Christ.</p>
            <p>And Christ saith (in the 15th of <hi>John</hi>) who hath all power in Heaven and Earth given to him;
<note place="margin">Christ's Law of Love.</note>
               <hi>This is my Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That you love one another, as I loved you:</hi> So, have not Christendom cast this Commandment of his behind their backs? for have they loved one another, or observed the Commandment of him that has all power? but instead of this, they have persecuted one another; and so cast away the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Jesus, as they Jews did the Law of God, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204659:4"/>not walkt in it; <hi>For herein,</hi> saith Christ, <hi>is my father glorified, that you bear much fruit; as the Father loved me, so have I love you; continue ye in my love:</hi> so Christians not continuing in the Love of Christ, with which he has loved them, they cannot bring forth fruits, so they cannot glorifie Christ, not the Father; <hi>For if you keep my Commandments you abide in my Love, even as I have kept my Fathers Commandment, and abide in his Love.</hi> So here Christians may see, they that abide not in the Love, but in the Enmity, they have not kept the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Christ: <hi>And ye are my Friends, if ye do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever I command you; and this is my Commandment, that you love one another, as I loved you:</hi> And so its plain, that these called Christians, that loves not one another, are no Friends to Christ Jesus, neither regards his Power nor Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Mark Christs words further, where he saith, <hi>Remember the words I said unto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 15.</note>
               <hi>The Servant is not greater then the Lord; if they have persecuted me, they will also persecute you; if they have kept my sayings, they will keep yours also.</hi> But now, mark, Christians,
<note place="margin">Such as persecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, act contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Christ's command.</note> you that do persecute are out of Christ's Mind, and Power, and Command, who saith, Love Enemies, and Love one another; and so, they that do persecute, has neither kept the sayings of Christ, nor the sayings of the Apostles: so all you that profess your selves to be Christians, and owns Christ Jesus, and that God hath sent him, you are not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute one another, nor Enemies; but the Command of Christ (to whom all power in Heaven and Earth is given) is to you, to love one another, for that edifies the body, and overcomes the Evil; and that is the Law of Love that is to be among Christians; and this is the Royal-Law from him that hath all power, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; and this Love bears all things, endures all things, hopes all things, is not provoked; for that which is provoked will run into Words and Actions, Enmity and Persecution, Malice and Hatred, which are the works of the Flesh, which is judged all down by the Law of Love; so keep the Law of Love, you keep down that which would be provoked: So Love over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Enmity, and the Light overcomes the Darkness,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204659:4"/>and the Righteousness overcomes the Unrighteousness, as Life overcomes Death and the Power of it, and so Good overcomes the Evil: So where is this universal Life, and universal Love amongst you Christians, whereby you might come out of your Narrow Spirit, and Garments, into a Large and Infinite Spirit?</p>
            <p>And Christ who taught his Christian Disciples to pray, who has all Power in Heaven and Earth given to him, which is a Common-Prayer to all <hi>Christendom,</hi> for all can say it, and saith it, in words;
<note place="margin">Christians ought to forgive, as they would be forgiven.</note>
               <hi>Forgive us our Debts as we forgive our Debtors; For if ye forgive men their Trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you: But if ye forgive not men their Trespasses, neither will your Father forgive you your Trespasses:</hi> and this Prayer differed from the Pharisees, who stood praying in the Synagogues, and did not forgive, as Christians now, who says this Common-Prayer of Christ to God the Father, Forgive us, as we do forgive them that Trespass against us; and that is, they ask no forgiveness at all for themselves, if they do not forgive. Oh, that they would come to that by which they might see their Blindness, and the Chain that they are under: For if Christians do transgress and trespass one against ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their Religions and Worships; the <hi>Papist</hi> against the <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> against the <hi>Papist,</hi> they must forgive one another: and the <hi>Presbyterian, Baptist, Independant, Lutheran Calvenists,</hi> Do not you all profess Christ, and God that sent him? Do you not all say Christ's Common-Prayer? And have you not trespassed one against another in matters of Religion, and Worship, and Church? Then must you not all forgive one another, according to Christs Prayer, who has all power in Heaven, &amp;c? And if you ask the Lord to be forgiven, as you do forgive, and you do not forgive;
<note place="margin">The Quakers can, and do forgive you all; and say the Lords Prayer in truth.</note> then you ask for no forgiveness: For, mark your words, you ask, to forgive us, as we do forgive them that trespass against us; so, mark the word [as] as you forgive, so you would be forgiven, and no otherwise: And so as you do Persecute, and cast in Prison, and Banish one another called Christians, and keep the Debts in your Books; Think you not that your Debts stands in Gods Book; and that he will Banish you from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204659:5"/>the Land of the Living, and cast you into Everlasting Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment, from the Presence of God and his Angels, as you may read the Dreadful Sentence in <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. wherein Christ saith to them that are the Goats, on the left hand; (Mark, they are on the left hand, and not one the right hand; for it is the Sheep are on the right hand) <hi>Depart from me, ye cursed, into Everlasting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels. For I was an hungry, and you gave me no meat: I was thirsty, you gave me no drink:</hi> Mark, these were them on the left hand, let them be called Christians, or whosoever they be: and they on the left hand are forwarder to take meat and drink from Christ, and his little ones, then to give it them; and to cast them into Prison till death, for their Bellies; but those are such as the Apostle speaks on, <hi>That serves not the Lord Jesus Christ, but their own Bellies.</hi> And Christ further saith, <hi>I was a stranger, and you took me not in: and naked, and you clothed me not: sick, and in prison, and you visited me not.</hi> And they on the left hand shall answer and say unto Christ, <hi>When saw we thee hungry, or a thirst, or a stranger, or naked, sick, or in prison, and did not minister unto thee?</hi> Hear Christ's answer to them; <hi>In as much as you did it not to one of the least of these, you did it not unto me:</hi> And therefore hear the Sentence of him, who hath all Power in Heaven and Earth, to them on the left hand, which are the Goats; <hi>Go away into Everlasting Punishment; but the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous into Life Eternal.</hi> Now they on the left hand, let them be called Christians, or what they will be, they are more like to make Strangers, then to take in Strangers, who banisheth them from their Wives and Families, and Native Land; and more like to make naked, and make sick, then to cloath, and to visit; and to imprison, then to visit in prison; and they that do so presseth the seed of God in themselves, from whence the Love of God flows; and such men do that which they should not do; for they should love one another; for it is the Angels work to Reap at the Harvest, which is the end of the World, and not mens; for it is Christ that is Judge it matters of Religion; for he doth, as you may see by the Talents, them that had improved them had their reward; and he that did not improve his Talent was an unprofitable Servant, <hi>to be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204659:5"/>cast into utter darkness, where shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth:</hi> And you that say, when shall this be? It is answered, <hi>When the Son of Man shall come in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him; then shall he sit upon the Throne of his glory, and before him shall be gathered all Nations; and he shall separate one from the other, as a Shepherd divideth the Sheep from the Goats; and he shall set the Sheep on his right hand, and the Goats on the left hand:</hi> So here it is plainly seen that Christ is the only Judge in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, and in dividing Sheep from Goates; so it is not man, in his own dark reason, that casts the Law of Christ Jesus behind his back (which is, <hi>to love one another</hi>) which ought to be his Rule, which is to be Judge in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>And as Christ saith, who hath all power in Heaven and Earth, <hi>Blessed are the Meek, for they shall inherit the Earth;</hi> [Mark] then they that are not meek do not inherit this bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: <hi>Blessed are they that hunger and thirst after Righteousness, they shall be filled;</hi> then they that hungers and thirsts after un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteousness, and drinks up iniquity, as an Ox drinketh up water, and persecutes the Righteous for his righteousness sake, they obtain not this blessing: <hi>Blessed be the Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for they shall obtain mercy;</hi> now the cruel, and the persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unmercifull obtain not this blessing: <hi>Blessed are the Pure in heart, for they shall see God;</hi> so the impure in heart, that loves the Evil, and hates the Light, and loves Darkness better then Light, doth not come to be partakers of this blessing, nor see God: <hi>Blessed are the Peace-makers, for they shall be called the Children if God;</hi> [mark] they that are the Strife-makers among people, for their Bellies, and outward things, are not the children of God, and have not this blessing: <hi>Blessed are they which are persecuted for Righteousness sake, for theirs is the Kingdom of God;</hi> then [mark] what blessing have the Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors? and what Kingdom is theirs, judge ye: <hi>Blessed are ye when men shall revile you, and persecute you, and say all manner of evil against you for my sake, and the Gospel;</hi> then it follows the Revilers and Persecutors have not that blessing.</p>
            <p>Query, <hi>What evil could any, both in the other Powers dayes, and now, find in the People called Quakers, but only concerning Christ, and their God; for which they have been Persecuted, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, and Imprisoned till Death?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:204659:6"/>
            <p>But here you may see Christ, who had all power in Heaven and Earth, did see that there would be Persecutors, and Speakers of all manner of evil against his People falsly, for his sake; but he encourages his Persecuted, and bids them <hi>rejoyce, and be glad exceedingly, for great is your reward in Heaven:</hi> So here you may see that their reward is not from the Earth; <hi>for so,</hi> said Christ, <hi>they persecuted the Prophets that went before you,</hi> which was to let them know that Persecution was no new thing; nevertheless Christ encourages them, that they are the Salt of the Earth, his children, and the Salt makes the Earth sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory; and they were the Light of the World, and a City set on a Hill cannot be hid; so that they could not be hid from the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors, and such as did speak all manner of evil against them falsly for his sake: And further Christ saith to encourage them, That the Light should be put in a Candlestick, and not under a Bushel to be hidden, but to give light to all the House; for they were the Light of the World; and bids them <hi>let their Light shine before men, that they might behold and see their good works, and glorifie their Father which is in Heaven;</hi> and this was to keep their eyes above them that persecuted, and spoke all manner of evil of them. And so here you may see that the Prophets, and the Children of the Kingdom did not suffer as just men in the eyes of the Persecutors; for <hi>Stephen</hi> did not suffer as a just man in the eyes of his Persecutors, but as a Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. And Christ Jesus, in the eyes of the Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Priests, Scribes and Pharisees, did not suffer by them as a just man, but was accounted a Deceiver; and the chief Priests <hi>mocked him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 15.</note>
               <hi>wagging their heads at him;</hi> and that is the way of the persecuting Spirit now; but Christ said, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do:</hi> And now you Christians that persecute, are you not so blind that you do not know what you do? And when the great persecuting professing Jews cried against Christ, <hi>Crucifie him, crucifie him,</hi> nothing but death would serve turn; did not Christ say to <hi>Pilate, If my Kingdom were of this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 18.</note>
               <hi>then would my servants fight, that I should not be delivered to the Jews; but now is my Kingdom not from thence;</hi> which shews, that the Kingdom of the world is the Fighters; and if Christ who had all power in Heaven and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204659:6"/>Earth given unto him would have defended himself against all his Persecutors, mocking Priests, and Professors; as you may see the greatest persecuting Professors in <hi>Christendom,</hi> they will now mock them they persecute; but such have cast the Law of Jesus behind their back; but Christ prayed to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to forgive his Persecutors, as the Quakers that have the mind of Christ do now, although he had all power given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and could have prayed unto his Father for Legions of Angels to defend him.</p>
            <p>And you read in the Scriptures that the great Professors of Scriptures, the Jews, said that Christ was a Deceiver, and he was mad, and had a Devil, and by the Prince of Devils cast out Devils; and Christ knew this was for Religion sake, and for his vertue and Sonship; and although he had all power in Heaven and Earth given unto him; yet he did not give forth any Law against them to have them punished, though they would have stoned him, and took up stones to stone him, who is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, he did not give forth any Command or Warrant to bind any to their good behaviour; for he suffered for his good profession and testimony: And oh, People, all that call your selves Christians, lift up your Eyes, that Christ may ye your Example, and follow him, not the Man of Sin, who was a Persecutor, Caster into Prison, and Murtherer from the beginning; for the proof, you may see in the <hi>Revelations</hi> its said,
<note place="margin">Rev. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>the Devil shall cast some of you in Prison ten dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> said to Christ, <hi>Lord how oft shall my Brother sin against me, and I forgive him, till seven times?</hi> Jesus said unto him, <hi>I say not unto thee not until seven times, but until seventy seven times.</hi> Oh, ye people that call your selves Christians, how unlike minded are you unto Christ in this? how short narrow and impatient spirited are you that persecute one another, and cannot bear one another, and forgive one another, and be patient one towards another, and love one another? And so Christ after he had spoken to <hi>Peter,</hi> he spoke a Parable, how that <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven is likened to a certain King which would take account of his Servants:</hi> [mark] <hi>and when he began to reckon, one was brought unto him which owed him ten thousand
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204659:7"/>Talents; but forasmuch as he had not to pay, his Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mmand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to be sold, and his wife and children, and all that he had, and payment to be made; the Servant fell down, and said, Lord, have pitty upon me, and I will pay thee all: then the Lord of that Servant was moved with compassion, and loosed him, and forgave him the debt:</hi> [mark] here is a Mercy, and the compassion, and the loosing, and the forgiveness in the acknowledgment from the Lord the King of Heaven; <hi>But the same Servant went out end found one of his fellow-servants which owed him one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pence; he laid hands of him, and took him by the throat, saying, Pay me that thou owest me; and though his fellow-servant said he would pay him, and besought him to have patience, and he would pay him all, he cast him into Prison till he paid the debt.</hi> Is not this like unto the envious, unmercifull, impatient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing Jews and Christians, that are so passionate and mad, and casting into Prison for every small matter; yea, and some that ows them nothing, neither sets them on work, as instance, the Priests and Bishops. So his fellow-servant was sorry, and saw what was done, and came and told his Lord; then the Lord called him unto him, and said, <hi>I forgave thee all the debt, O wicked servant, because thou desirest me; shouldst not thou have had compassion on thy fellow servant, as I had pitty on thee? And his Lord was wroth, and delivered him unto the Tormentor, until he had paid him all his due unto him: So,</hi> says Christ, <hi>likewise shall my Heavenly Father do unto you; if ye from your hearts for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give not every one his Brother their Trespasses.</hi> Oh, ye that are called Christians, and goes by the Name, that are so subject, and so forward to take your Brother by the Throat, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them into Prison till your will be satisfied, and makes your brothers trespassers, when they are none, and cast them into Prison, when you have neither Law nor ground, but to satisfie your wills; consider the Sentence of Christ, how that he said his Heavenly Father will deliver you up to the Tormentors, till that you have paid him his due, who do not forgive your Brethren from your hearts which trespass against you; nay, many of you cannot forgive that which is no trespass, but with spleen and envy will revenge; For would you take Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance out of Gods hand?
<note place="margin">Matth. 18.</note> who saith, <hi>Vengeance is his, and he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204659:7"/>would repay it;</hi> and every one that doth wrong shall receive for the wrong that he doth, and God respects no mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; and so this might convince you, Let the Tares and the Wheat grow together till the Harvest; for God would give them their reward according to their deeds, whether they be good or evil. Let all <hi>Christendom</hi> lay away this Law of Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting one another, and so make no more; but mind that which is made already by Christ Jesus, who hath all power in Heaven and Earth, which is the Law of Love, and the great Commandment, <hi>To love one another, and Enemies,</hi> and this is that must unite all <hi>Christendom</hi> to a uniformity and conformity to their Head Christ Jesus, their Law-maker, and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-giver.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. Christ saith, <hi>Thou shalt love thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy self, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy soul, and with all thy mind; and on these two Commandment hangs the Laws and the Prophets:</hi> this spoke Christ of the Lawyers when they came to ensnare him by their Laws, as many do now the children of his Kingdom: So now [mark] how short are you, called Christians, of the Law and the Prophets, in the practice of Christs Doctrine; for if you loved your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as your selves, then, how can you imprison? How can you bannish? how can you spoil goods? how can you burn? how can you hang your Neighbour? how can you love and serve God with all your hearts and your souls, and destroy the Creatures, the works of his hands, and for matter of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Worship of God, whom you profess to love? And seeing you all do profess God and Christ, and yet do destroy one another about your Religion and Worship, this is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his Command who has all power in Heaven and Earth; this is contrary to his Command, which is to love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Enemies, and contrary to his Law of Love, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Doctrine and Example,
<note place="margin">Matth. 12.</note>
               <hi>who came not to destroy mens lives, but to save them;</hi> who rebuked them that would have had mens lives destroyed; and <hi>to do unto all men, as you would have them do unto you;</hi> Mark this Royal-Law and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and cast it not out from amongst you; for you would not have any man to persecute you, or imprison you; would you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204659:8"/>have any to banish you, and put you to death for your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Worship? Or would you have any man to spoil your Goods, and to have you from your Families, and to keep you in Prison till death, and while your wives are made wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and children fatherless for your Religion? and so, that which you would not have men do unto you, do not you unto others; for the Royal-Law of Liberty respects no mans person; and so do unto others, as you would have others do unto you, and this keeps all to an even Ballance, and just weight; and so observe the Royal-Law of Liberty.</p>
            <p>The two Sons of <hi>Zebedee</hi> when their mother came with them to Christ, and desired of him that her two Sons should sit one of his right hand, and the other on the left hand in his Kingdom; and when the ten other Disciples heard it, they were moved with indignation against the two Brethren; here you may see what caused indignation, that is, one Disciple to be above another; but Jesus, who has all power in Heaven and Earth, to take away this offence, and clear all, and stop all, he called the Disciples to him, and said, [mark] <hi>Ye know that the Princes of the Gentiles exercise dominion over them, and they are called gracious lords;</hi> [mark] <hi>but it shall not be so among you;</hi> and this was to keep the Ministers of the Gospel equal Brethren, and not to exercise Lordship and Authority one over another in matters of Religion and Faith; for it was the Gentiles that exercised Lordship: and to confirm this, he said, <hi>Whosoever will be chief among you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.</note>
               <hi>let him be as Servant; and the Son of Man came not to be ministred unto, but to minister, and to give his Life a ransom for all: And be not ye called of men</hi> Rabbi, <hi>for one is your Master even Christ, and you are all Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> and so not to be called Lord like the Gentiles. And Christ said by way of prophesie, how that the Jews, and others, <hi>should kill, and crucifie, and scourge, and persecute in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, and from City to City, that upon you may come all the righteous blood shed upon the Earth, from the blood of righteous</hi> Abel, <hi>to the blood of</hi> Zacharias <hi>son of</hi> Barachias, <hi>whom you slew betwixt the Temple and the Altar.</hi> And so, upon whom must all the righteous blood come upon that has been shed in all Christendom, about Religion, since Christ and the Apostles
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:204659:8"/>dayes, who have manifested the spirit of the Jews in scourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your Synagogues, and from place to place, such as Christ has sent amongst you?</p>
            <p>And did not Christ say, <hi>How can ye,</hi> that follow such practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which he calls a Generation of Vipers, <hi>escape the damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Hell?</hi> and therefore said he, <hi>Be you Witnesses, that you are the children of them that killed the Prophets;</hi> and so is not the same to be said to you that persecutes now? Be you Witnesses, that you are the children of them that killed Christ and the Apostles, and his Witnesses, and Saints and Martyrs that kept the Testimony of Jesus since the Apostles dayes; fill up the measure of your fore fathers. And did not Christ say, <hi>Oh Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem, Jerusalem, thou that killest the Prophets, and stoned them that are sent unto thee, how oft would I have gathered thee, as a Hen gathereth her Chickens under her wings, but ye would not? Behold your Houses is left desolate unto you.</hi> Was not <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi> the highest place of Profession, where those Persecutors, Murtherers, and killers of the Lords Prophets lived? And what may be said of <hi>Christendom,</hi> and her highest place of Worship, look both among Papists and Protestants? how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have they killed and persecuted that were sent among them by Christ? Do you think that Christ doth not weep over you, whom you thus daily pierce, and if the Persecutors Houses at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> were to be left desolate; then what will become of your Houses, who call your selves Christians, and yet are found Persecutors? Do you think that all Persecutors Houses will not be left desolate, though they be never so high Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors of the Scriptures; will not their Houses be left desolate of God and Christ? read <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. And doth not Christ say, <hi>If thou hast any thing against thy Brother, leave thy gift at the Altar, and go and be reconciled to thy Brother, and then offer it:</hi> And so should not all the Christians in the whole World be reconciled to one another before they offer their gift to God and Christ, whose Law is, <hi>They should love one another,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas it is said in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all men: Love the Brotherhood: Fear God: and Honour the King.</hi> [Mark] To fear God, is not to grieve nor offend him, but to be subject to him, and reverence him; to honour all men, and to honour the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204659:9"/>King, is to have the King, and all men in esteem, and to esteem the King is not to hurt the King, nor no man; and this lays wast all persecution and Persecutors: for how can they say they esteem the King, or esteem any man, if they perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him; and so as all true Christians are Brethren in Christ Jesus, they are to love the Brotherhood, and so to keep the Law and Command of Christ; and one Christian persecuting another about Religion and Worship, doth not love the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood.</p>
            <p>And at the Councel of the great professing Jews, when the Apostles were brought before the Councel and high Priests, and <hi>they charged them they should preach no more in the Name of Jesus:</hi> Then answered the Apos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les to them, <hi>Whether they ought to obey God rather then man, judge ye:</hi> And the Apostle said further to them, <hi>The God of our fore-fathers has raised <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p Jesus whom you slew and hanged on a tree, and God hath exalted him at his right hand to be a Prince, and a Saviour, and to give repentance to</hi> Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>and forgiveness of sins,</hi> and the Apostle said, <hi>We are Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses of these things, &amp;c.</hi> When the Councel heard these things, they who had before slain the Son, took counsel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether how they might slay the Apostles. Here all may see this persecuting, murthering spirit, that persecuted in all Ages; who may say now, had we been in the dayes of Christ and the Apostles, we would not have killed them, so they that do persecute may see they be in the same spirit as the Persecutors were in the Apostle dayes, and not in the Spirit of Christ and the Apostles: but then stood up one in the Councel, when they took Councel to kill the Apostles, who was a Pharisee, named <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> a Doctor of the Law, had in repute among all the People, and commanded to put the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles forth a little space; and said unto them, <hi>Ye men of</hi> Israel, <hi>take heed to your selves what ye do touching these men,</hi> when he had convinced them by many arguments, as from verse 36 to 37 of <hi>Acts</hi> 6. <hi>Let them alone,</hi> said he, <hi>for if this Counsel or this Work be of men, it will come to naught; but if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it, lest happily ye be found Fighters against God.</hi> So to this <hi>Gamaliel</hi> the Councel and high Friest agreed, and and called the Apostles, whom they beat, and commanded
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204659:9"/>them to speak no more in the Name of Jesus; yet the Apostles departed rejoycing that they were counted worthy to suffer for his Name; and the Apostles went and taught daily afterwards in the Temple, and every house, Christ Jesus: Now [mark] would some in our dayes say the Apostles brought sufferings upon their own heads, and that they did it to provoke the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, as some in our dayes have said; and you may see this persecuting Councel though they had agreed to <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> yet they must persecute the Apostles; has not them called Christians in <hi>Christendom</hi> wanted this <hi>Gamaliel</hi> amongst them for to moderate, and to stay them from banishing, killing, burning, prisoning, spoiling of good, and so to moderate them? For this <hi>Gamaliel</hi> was a sew, and Christians thinks themselves above a Jew: but where is the <hi>Gamaliels</hi> spirit amongst you, that says, <hi>If it be of God it will stand;</hi> shewing, that he knew not whether it were of God or no? And where is <hi>Gamaliel</hi>'s caution in <hi>Christendom? Let them alone, restrain your selves, if it be of God it will stand; if it be the work of men, it will come to nought; if it be of God you cannot overthrow it: therefore take heed lest you be found fighters against God.</hi> And therefore, what became of all the Jews that were found Fighters against God and Christ? And what is become of the Pope, and all them persecuting Powers before you? And has not the Pope lost more then all <hi>Christendom?</hi> And so if there be not a <hi>Gamaliel</hi>'s spirit and counsel amongst you, to moderate the persecuting spirit, mind <hi>Gamaliel</hi>'s counsel in <hi>Acts</hi> 5. For indeed the true Christians are above <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> for they know that which they preach to be of God, though the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Gamaliel</hi> (whose spirit is beyond the spirit that is in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom)</hi> cried, if it were of God it would stand, and so stopt them from violent persecution: so had not the Christian Priests and Bishops need of such a <hi>Gamaliel</hi> to moderate and regulate them, and hold their reins from posting on to perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: And doth not the Apostle say, <hi>That Christians should not bite one another, lest they should devour and consume one anc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but love one another,</hi> and so fulfill the Law of Christ Jesus, which is the Law of Love, for the Law of Love that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves, and if they keep the Law of Love, they will not bite
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204659:10"/>one another, nor consume one another, nor persecute one another, nor spoil one another as they have done.</p>
            <p>And the Apostle saith to the Christians in the Primitive times, before the Apostacy came in, <hi>For though we walk in the Flesh</hi> said he, <hi>we do not War after the Flesh, for the weapons of our warfare are not carnal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians weapons, and wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is they war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst.</note>
               <hi>but spiritual, mighty through God to the pulling done of strong holds, casting down of every imagination, and every high thought that exalts its self against the knowledge of God, bringing into Captivity every thought to the obedience of Christ,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 4, 5. Now [mark] the strong holds, the high imaginations and high thoughts were not brought down by carnal weapons, nor that which exalts it self against the knowledge of God, but by spiritual weapons; and here it is clear that one Christian did not persecute another with carnal weapons; for their war was not after the flesh, nor their wrestling was not with flesh and blood; and that which gives the knowledge of God is the Light which shines in the heart; and persecutors since the Apostles dayes, instead of plucking down the imaginations and high thoughts, and to bring that down to the obedience of Christ, which exalts its self, which is the Spirits work, they wrestled with flesh and blood since the Apostles dayes, and warred after the flesh, not having the Power as the Apostles had: and so having lost the Apostles warfare and weapons, which were spiritual, and gotten carnal in the room of them, and the Apostle also spake to the <hi>Ephesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who were the Christians in the primitive times, he said, <hi>My Brethren, be strong in the Lord, and in the Power of his Might, and put on the whole Armor of God, that you may be able to stand against the wiles of the Devil:</hi> [Mark] this was Gods Armor, and not Mans, <hi>having their loyns girt with Truth, and the Brest-plate of Salvation; and their feet shod with the preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Gospel of Peace, and taking the Shield of Faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you shall be able to squench all the fiery darts of the wicked, and take the Homet of Salvation, and the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God:</hi> [mark] these were the weapons of the Christians in the primitive times which they warred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and wrestled withal against Principalities and Powers, Rulers of darkness of this World, and spiritual wickedness in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204659:10"/>high places; <hi>For,</hi> saith he, <hi>we do not wrestle against Flesh and Blood;</hi> so here it is plain that the primitive Christians did not use carnal weapons, Clubs and Staves, like <hi>Judas</hi> his Company, to persecute and hale one another, or those that were of a different mind to them to Prison, or Banish them; for if they had, they must have used carnal weapons, and wrestled with Flesh and Blood; so with spiritual wickedness they wrestled with the spiritual weapons, which weapons the Apostate Christians are degenerated from, and therefore took up carnal; and we know, and you do know, that the Shield of Faith, and the Brest-plate of Righteousness, and the Helmet of Salvation, and the Sword of the Spirit, and the Word of of God, and the feet shod with the Gospel of Truth to be the Girdle; these be the Spiritual weapons, and this is the Armor of God which the Christians in the primitive times used, by which they did not wrestle with Flesh and Blood,
<note place="margin">The true Christians A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mor in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, and the false since.</note> nor war after the Flesh with carnal weapons; and they that have warred after the Flesh with carnal weapons since the Apostles dayes about Religion and Church, are in that spirit and power that the Apostles and primtive Christians warred against, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Scriptures in their carnal minds, warring and wrest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with blesh and Blood, which are judged and reproved by the Apostles and primitive Christians words.</p>
            <p>And the Christians in the primitive times,
<note place="margin">Ephes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10, to 18.</note> the Apostles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was to them, they were not to avenge themselves, but rather to give place to wrath, <hi>For Vengeance is mine saith the Lord, and I will repay it;</hi> and so they were to follow peace with all men, &amp; holiness, without which no man should see the Lord, <hi>not to render evil for evil, nor railing for railing; but contrariwise blessing, knowing that they are thereunto called, that they should in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blessing,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.9. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. And they were to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come evil with good, and thou shalt heap coals of fire on his head in so doing: therefore, if possible, as much as in you lies live peaceably with all men, recompence to no man evil for evil. Now people you may see how this Doctrine and practice of the primitive Christians is laid aside in Christendom by <hi>such as have the Form of godliness, but deny the Power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note>
               <hi>who are to be turned away from,</hi> who have rendred evil for evil, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204659:11"/>takes revenge, as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. And the Apostle said, <hi>Every soul must be subject to the Higher Power;</hi> [mark] the Soul is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and the Power is so; for he says, <hi>There is no Powers but it is of God, and the Powers that be are ordained of God, and he that resisteth the Power, resisteth the Ordinance of God;</hi> so the Power is not to be spoke against, nor resisted; for it being ordained of God the soul must be subject to it, <hi>for Rulers are not a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to good works, but to evil: Wilt thou then not be afraid of the Power? Do that which is good, and thou shalt have praise of the same:</hi> [mark] this Power is not against the good, but against the evil, it is not a terror to the good, but to the evil; the good has its praise by the Power, and is not afraid of it; but the evil is afraid, and it is a terror to it; <hi>so he is a Minister of God to thee for good; but he that doth evil is afraid of the Power, for he heareth not the Sword in vain; for he is the Minister of God to revenge the wrath upon him that doth evil:</hi> So [mark] not upon the good, so here he makes a distinction, the Good from the Evil, the Higher Power is a praise to the good; wherefore we must needs be subject <hi>not only for wrath, but also for conscience sake,</hi> that is, to be subject to the Power that is a praise to the good, and a terror to the evil: now when Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates acted contrary to the Power (as you may read in the Scripture) ordained of God, then he sent his Prophets and Servants to cry against the corruptions of the Magistrates, not against the Power which God had ordained, and such Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates if they did not return to the Power; you may read how often God overturned them; and such Magistrates you may see often in the Scriptures turned the Sword backwards against the Righteous, and let the Guilty go free, and made no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the precious and the vile; and for this cause have we paid the tribute and dues; so custom to whom custom, honour to whom honour, fear to whom fear; so we have not been behind on our parts, they have had their tribute, and the Magistrates their Customs and their dues, though they have turned their sword against us, against the good, and Drunkards, Swearers, and Evil-doers at liberty; so we have not been behind on our hands, though they have been on theirs, but we leave them all to the Lord to plead with all in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204659:11"/>the cause: and the Apostle saith to the Christians, <hi>Owe nothing to any man, but love one another, for love fulfils the Law;</hi> so they that do not love another, and be out of Love, it is clear do not fulfil the Law, but break it; And are not Christians great Debters in this? and the Apostle saith, <hi>Thou shalt not commit adultery, nor kill, nor steal, nor bear falfe witness, nor covet,</hi> if there be any other Commandment, it is briefly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in this saying, <hi>Thou shalt love thy Neighbour as thy self;</hi> and here its clear this Higher Power, which Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters attend upon continually, is not against the liberty of true Christians, nor does not take hold upon people in matters of Religion and Worship, but such as kills, commits adultery, steals and Covets; here is nothing of this Higher Powers medling with difference in Religion, or to be any terror to them, but to the evil doers; but this Higher Power is a praise to all that own God, and profess Christ Jesus, and live in his Life; and all Christians are <hi>to stand fast in the Liberty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Christ hath made them Free:</hi> now the Apostle, who said, <hi>Tribute to whom tribute, and custom to whom custom,</hi> this was to the Magistrates, and that they should have their dues, this doth not concern the Priests Tythes; for the Apostle plainly declared against Tythes, and said, <hi>The Law was changed by which the Priesthood was made, and the Commandment disannul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led which gave Tythes,</hi> Hebr. 7. and he preach'd up another Priest-hood, <hi>Christ Jesus made higher then the Heavens:</hi> now as the Apostle saith, <hi>Love works no evil to its Neighbour, and Love is the fulfilling of the Law,</hi> and this keeps him out of killing, stealing, committing adultery, and bearing false wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and this keeps him from under the Magistrates Sword, who is subject to the Power which is a praise to him that does well; and he that loves his Neighbour as himself, he will not kill his Neighbour, nor bear false witness against him, nor steal from him, nor commit adultery, for those are the actions of the Evil-doer the Law is a Terror against, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, to v. 10.</p>
            <p>The Apostle saith to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> the Law is fulfilled in one word, <hi>Thou shalt love thy Neighbour as thy self,</hi> so if the Law be fulfilled, then it doth not take hold upon such that love their Neighbour as their selves; and ye that be led by the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204659:12"/>Spirit of God, you are not under the Law; for they that are led by the evil spirit into Drunkeness, Envy, and Murther, and Strife, and full of Hatred, such Fruits comes under the Law, and the Higher Power is a terror to them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. And they that loves their Neighbour as themselves, do not bite nor devour nor consume one another; but they that do hate their Neighbours, and bite and consume one another, these do not fulfil the Law, but break it; as cast your eye over <hi>Christendom,</hi> and you may see these Fruits;
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> and the Persecution came for the Cross of Christ sake, which Cross was the Power, before the Wood and Stone one was; and therefore them that do persecute be out of the Higher Power, and Cross, and Life of Christ Jesus.</p>
            <p>And the Apostle says to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.</note>
               <hi>We know the Law is good, if a man use it lawfully;</hi> now [mark] a man must use it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and then its good, <hi>Knowing this,</hi> saith the great Apostle of Christ Jesus, <hi>that the Law is not made for a righteous man;</hi> therefore they that be righteous men, and the Quakers which no evil can be charged against them in their lives and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations,
<note place="margin">[Mark] The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops they have not observed the sound Order the Apostle wrote to <hi>Timothy.</hi>
               </note> the Law is not to be laid upon them, if it be used law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; for, saith the great Apostle, <hi>the Law was made for the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, disobedient, for sinners, unholy, prophane, murtherers of fathers and mothers, man-slayers, whoremongors, such as defile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with mankind, men-stealers, lyars, perjured persons,</hi> to such the Law is a terror, for these be the Evil-doers, which Law is a praise to them that be good; and so the Law here was not made to limit people from worshipping of God, that owned God and Christ, but for such above mentioned, and this is according to sound Doctrine, and also according to the blessed Gospel of God, which was committed to the Apostles trust, which he taught and laid down to be observed amongst the Primitive Christians, which others, apostatised from his Life are degenerated from, and have not observed his sound Doctrine, but many have turned the Sword backward, and the Laws upon righteous men, which it was not made for, and that has not been according to the glorious Gospel of the blessed God, nor according to the Higher Power, but the lower from whence persecution has arisen.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:204659:12"/>
            <p>When the Pharisees took counsel how they might entangle Christ in his talk, they sent from their Councel their Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with the <hi>Herodians,</hi> saying, <hi>We know, Master, that thou art true, neither carest thou for any man, for thou regardest not the person of men, tell us therefore, what thinkest thou, is it lawfull to give tribute to</hi> Caesar, <hi>or not?</hi> Jesus perceiving their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, said, <hi>Why tempt you me, ye Hypocrites? shew me the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute money, and they brought unto him a penny, he said unto them, Whose is this image and superscription? they said unto him</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sars: <hi>then said he unto them, Render therefore unto</hi> Caesar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caesars, <hi>and to God the things that are Gods.</hi> [Mark] those that came to tempt Christ were of the Jews, the great Professors, and <hi>Caesar</hi> was a Heathen, and the Jews being under the Power of the Heathen, having lost the Life of that which they did profess, that spirit in them would have brought Christ under <hi>Caesar,</hi> by the temptations; and these he calls Hypocrites, who professed the Scriptures, and were not in the Life of them, as all others are at this day, who are found in the same nature that would ensnare; but Christ, who is the Wisdom of God, confounded them. And <hi>Caesar</hi> must have his things, and what are his things, but his tribute, his custom, and from that which his superscription is upon? And so other Kings whose Image is set upon their money, must have their dues: But [mark] people God must have his things in the midst of <hi>Caesar</hi> the Heathen, and the Councel of the great professing Jews; and what are Gods things? where his Image and Superscription is written in the Heart, God must have his things; so see each Superscription and Image. So let <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar</hi> have his due where his Superscription and Image is; so the Superscription and Image of <hi>Caesar</hi> to <hi>Caesar,</hi> and Gods Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Image to himself; for the Holy One must have his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and not to be limitted, and so here every thing is in its place. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.17.</p>
            <p>As the Apostle saith, <hi>Whatsoever is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> Rom. 14.23. shewing, that the true Faith is not sin, for it is that which gives the victory and access to God, and purifies the heart; and therefore to bring People to that which is not of Faith, is to bring them into sin, and to make them to make
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204659:13"/>shipwrack of their Faith and of a good Conscience, seeing that the mystery of Faith is held in the good and pure Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; therefore the true Faith must have its liberty, which gives the victory, in which God is pleased, and who are of Faith are of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the great Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> saith to the <hi>Corinthians, That we have not dominion or power over your Faith, but we are helpers of your joy, for by Faith ye stand.</hi> Now [mark] all ye that be in <hi>Christendom,</hi> that calls your selves Christians, who persecutes about Religion, have not you degenerated from the Apostles, that would have dominion and power over mens Faith? Is not the case plain, that you would not have the Faith which is the gift of God have its liberty? and that you be out of the true Faith, the gift of God, which the Apostles were in; and so are no helpers of the joy of them that are in the true Faith, you your selves not standing by it: And why did the Apostle bid them stand fast in the Faith, as knowing there was some would oppose their Faith? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24.</p>
            <p>And were not the Apostles a Councel amongst themselves, for doth he not say, <hi>We have not dominion or power over your Faith;</hi> for if they had said they had power over their Faith, they might have said they had power over the Gift of God, for <hi>Faith was the Gift of God;</hi> and that they had power over Christ, <hi>who was the Author of Faith, and Finisher of it;</hi> but the Apostle said, <hi>They were helpers of one anothers joy in the Faith they were to build up one another in:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Men must not have power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mens Faith.</note> so its clear that God must have his liberty to give his Faith, and Chist must have his liberty, who is the Author and Finisher of Faith, which men must not have power over, no not the Apostles, for by one Faith they all stand.</p>
            <p>And the Gospel which the Apostles preached, which they <hi>had not received of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Men ought to have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel.</note>
               <hi>nor by man, but by the revelation of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, which was the Power of God unto Salvation to every one that believeth;</hi> this Gospel, the Power of God, which is Liberty, is to have its liberty, and men must have their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it; for if men turn against the Power, they turn against the Gospel, and bring destruction upon themselves, in turning against, and persecuting the Power of God, and their own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:204659:13"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:204659:14"/>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:204659:14"/>
               <head>Now concerning the Act that prohibits, that not above four or five may meet.</head>
               <p>THis Act would have taken hold upon Christ and his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciples had he been in your dayes;
<note place="margin">The Act against the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers would have taken hold on Christ and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles.</note> Christ its known had twelve Apostles, and seventy Disciples which often met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and besides the great multitudes that met with Christ in the Towns, Wildernesses, and Mountains in the dayes of <hi>Caesar</hi> and the Jews, and you do not read that either <hi>Caesar,</hi> or the Jews made any Acts or Laws, that Christ and his Disciples should not meet together; though at last by that Law that they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> amongst themselves, they put him to death for saying that he was the Son of God. And did not the Romans which were Heathen, let the Jews have their Liberty to worship God, when they had power over them, though their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion differed from theirs, as you may read both in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and in <hi>Euscbeus</hi> and <hi>Josephus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, had not the Christians in <hi>Britain</hi> Liberty, and lived peaceably until <hi>Dicclesian</hi>'s time, and lived pretty quietly,
<note place="margin">When the Christians began first to suffer in <hi>England,</hi> and by whom.</note> though their Religion differed from the Heathens Religion in this Land? and in <hi>Dioclesian</hi>'s time many were persecuted to death at <hi>Litchfield</hi> and <hi>Leicester;</hi> but mark what was the end of his power. And did not many suffer persecution about six hundred years after Christ by <hi>Austin</hi> the Monk, when he brought over his Snapsack of Ceremonies; and caused not he many of the <hi>Britains</hi> to be destroyed, because they would not conform to the Ceremonies he brought from <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The three Children preserved, though cast into the fiery Furnace for not wo ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi>'s I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And had not the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> (though in Captivity in a strange Land) Liberty in the Empire of <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> though his Religion differed from theirs, until that <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar</hi> set up his golden Image, with all his Musick, who cast the three Children into the fiery Furnace because they would not worship it, who worshipped God, and did give to <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar</hi> the things that belonged to him, and to God the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship that belonged to him; and did not the Lord preserve these three Children that stood for him, &amp; worshipped him? and did not King <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> change his word and Decree which he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204659:15"/>had made to burn them that would not worship his Image, and make another Decree by which he gave Liberty to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Israel,</hi> and sent it among all his People and Nations, that they should not speak any thing amiss against the God of the Children of <hi>Israel?</hi> and did he not afterwards confess to the God of Heaven that his Kingdom was an everlasting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and his Dominion from Generation to Generation? And had not he the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> in great esteem, though they differed from his Nations Religion, Worship, Laws, and Manners, as you may read in <hi>Daniel</hi> the 3d and 4th chapters? And in <hi>Daniel</hi> chap. 5. <hi>Belshazzar</hi> his son, did he not give Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to the Children of <hi>Israel?</hi> but when this <hi>Belshazzar</hi> did meddle with the Vessels of the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey brought out of the Temple at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> was not there a Hand-Writing on the Wall against him? And so you that be in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>Babylon,</hi> that do meddle with the Vessels of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God and Jews in the Spirit, do you not think that the Hand-Writing is against you <hi>MENE TEKEL, You are found to light, being weighed in the Ballance; and do you not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide? and are not your years numbred?</hi> and doth not spiritual <hi>Babylon</hi> set up his spiritual Image, and Musick about it? and has not he burnt and persecuted such as cannot fall down to it, as you may read in the <hi>Cronicles,</hi> and in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> and yet is not come so far as <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> who altered his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and confessed to the God of Heaven, and gave Liberty to such as differed from his National worship? And had not <hi>Belshazzar</hi> a great esteem of the Jews though they differed from his Religion, and were Captives in his Country? and if it had been your day, would you not have said the three Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were disobedient and wilfull, because they would not fall down at the sound of the Musick, and worship his Image, who obeyed the Lord?</p>
               <p>And were it not some of the <hi>Caldeans</hi> that were the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers against the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> the outward Jews, that raised persecution against them? and are there not many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers now in spiritual <hi>Babylon,</hi> that raises persecution upon the Jews in the Spirit?</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Daniel</hi> 6. in the dayes of <hi>Darius</hi> Emperor, had not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204659:15"/>the Children of <hi>Irael</hi> Liberty under the Emperor in his Empire, though they differed from his National Worship and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, until that some of the Princes sought to find out a fault or occasion against him, but could find no fault, he being faithfull? Then said the men, <hi>We shall not find any thing against this</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, <hi>except we find it against him concerning the Law of his God.</hi> Now [mark] here you may see <hi>Daniel</hi> had Liberty concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law of his God, till this time, that they made a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, according to the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> which alters not, <hi>That whosoever asked any Petition for thirty dayes, saving of the King</hi> Darius, <hi>should be cast into the Lions Den.</hi> Now [mark] <hi>Daniel went into his house,</hi> after this Decree was made, <hi>his windows in his chamber being open towards</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>he kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down upon his knees three times a day, and prayed, and gave thanks before his God, as he had done before time.</hi> Now [mark] O ye Christians, would ye not say that <hi>Daniel</hi> was a very fool, and a wilfull rebellious person, as knowing the Kings Decree, and the spire of these men against him, and he having been formerly in favour with the King, to lose all, and endanger his life? these men finding <hi>Daniel</hi> praying to his God, inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King, and the Law was executed upon him: But mark how God preserved this <hi>Daniel,</hi> and how glad the King was of it, and what became of his Accusers, who were cast to the Lions and torn to pieces: and did not <hi>Darius</hi> then confess to the Living God, and his Kingdom, and made another Decree to give Liberty to <hi>Daniel</hi> and the Children of <hi>Israel?</hi> which <hi>Darius</hi> the Emperor wrote to all People, Nations and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages dwelling on the Earth, <hi>That they should all tremble and fear before the God of</hi> Daniel, <hi>for he is the Living God stedfast for ever; and his Kingdom shall not be destroyed, and his Dominion shall never have an end.</hi> And so had not <hi>Daniel</hi> and these Children of <hi>Israel</hi> Liberty in the Realm of <hi>Darius</hi> and <hi>Cyrus</hi> Kings of <hi>Persia</hi> and the <hi>Medes,</hi> though they differed from them in their Religion, and were Captives? and doth not this judge all Christians who professeth God and Christ, and are not to have power over one anothers Faith, and cannot give Liberty to one another, but persecute one another, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204659:16"/>to the command of Christ, who said they should love one another?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 39. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> who had been cast into the Dungeon, and set in the Stocks, and beaten for his testimony for the Lord by the persecuting Jews, who kept him in Prison till <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> carried away his Persecutor captive into <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon:</hi> the Captain of this <hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> guard, left of the poor of the People which had nothing in the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> and gave them Fields and Vineyards; and <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> gave charge to the Captain of his Guard concerning <hi>Jeremiah, Take him, and look well to him, do him no harm:</hi> And he took <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> out of the Court of the Prison, and said, <hi>This day I will loose thee from the Chain which is upon thy hand, if it seem good for thee to go with me into</hi> Babylon, <hi>I will look well unto thee; but if it seem evil unto thee to go into</hi> Babylon <hi>forbear; behold, all the Land is before thee, whether it seemeth good and convenient to go, thither go;</hi> and so <hi>Jeremiah</hi> staid in the Land of Judah. And now, Friends, was there not more mercy in this Heathen <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> then in the Jews and the great persecuting Professors? for though he had conquered the Land, yet he did not force <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> nor the People he left behind him, to be of his Religion, but left them to follow their own Religion in their own Land: And has not <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> outstript ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny People in this; as you may read in <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> chapters 38, 39, and 40?</p>
               <p>And have you not read in <hi>Ezra</hi> the Proclamation of <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Persia</hi> to all the Jews among his People throughout all his hingdom, how that the Jews might go up and build their Temple, and what large Liberty was given to them, and how that they might have Liberty to go and serve and worship God? and though the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> were of another Religion then the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> yet he gave the Children of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> liberty; but it was the Lord stirred up the Spirit of this <hi>Cyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> King of <hi>Persia</hi> to give Liberty to worship God, and serve him; then people may judge what it is that stirs up the spirits of people to persecute people for worshipping of God, <hi>Ezra</hi> 1. And did not a People rise up to persecute the Jews
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204659:16"/>afterwards, and called them a rebellious people, under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that if they built a Temple, they should damage the King, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. But afterwards the Persecutors end was frustra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> went on in their work. And so this <hi>Darius</hi> made another Decree for the Jews Liberty, and the building the Temple, <hi>And whosoever should alter a word of the Decree, the Timber should be pluck'd down from his house, and being set up, he was to be hanged thereon, and his house to be made a Dunghil; and the Children of</hi> Israel <hi>were to pray for the life of the King and his Sons.</hi> And so here you may see what Liberty this man, called a Heathen, gave to the outward Jews, who differed from him in Religion, who was a Heathen; and what a strict Decree he made against them that were against the Jews, and would have hindred them from building the Temple; and so this Decree was for the service of God, against his own Religion, which Temple now Christ has ended, and the Priests and Jews Services, <hi>and he is not a few that is one outward;</hi> so that Command, Decree and Penalty of <hi>Darius</hi> is ended, for such a work; <hi>for he is a Jew who is one inward now, whose Weapons are Spiritual and not Carnal; but the Inward Temple comes to be raised up by the Spirit, and the Law and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Jesus observed, to love one another;</hi> yet <hi>Darius</hi> may judge the persecuting spirit in Christians; for <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> made a Decree that whatsoever <hi>Ezra</hi> the Priest the Scribe of the Law of the God of Heaven should require of them, should be done for the House of the God of Heaven, for why should there be wrath against the Realm of the King and his Son; and so <hi>Ezra</hi> was to set Magistrates and Judges, and such as knew the Law, and taught them that knew it not; <hi>And whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever would not do the Law of God, and the Law of the King, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was to be executed speedily upon him, whether unto death, or unto banishment,</hi> Ezra 7. And now here you may see what Liberty this <hi>Artaxerzes</hi> gave to the Jews, who were of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Religion from him, that they that did not obey his Heathen Law, and the Law of God, it was death; and so he makes a distinction betwixt his Law and the Law of God, though he was a Heathen; but <hi>Ezra</hi> the Priest, and the Levites, and the primitive Priesthood, with all their Offerings, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204659:17"/>their Temple, Christ has ended that Priesthood, and the Law by which it was made, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. And so, as for Banishing put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Death, Imprisoning, confiscation of Goods concerning the building the Jews Temple, and Sacrificing there, with their Singers and Ministers, Christ his ended all these, and says, <hi>Love one another,</hi> not banish, nor spoil one anothers Goods; so his Command now is to be observed, and not <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> nor <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> to build the Temple of the Jews, and offer Sacrifice: now this may condemn the Christians, (for a Heathen to give his Law, and to promote the Jews, and the Law of God by which the Religion stood,) who makes Laws to persecute one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrary to the Law and Command of Jesus, which saith, <hi>Love one another;</hi> for where did you ever read of any Law the Christians made, That they should love one another, and that they should keep the Command of Christ, who saith, Love one another, and not spoil the Goods, and banish one another? If not, has not <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> condemned them, who by his Heathen Law promotes the Law of God, and the Jews Religion? which Religion and Law of the Jews Christ has ended, as Offerings, Sacrifices, and Temple, as I said before, <hi>For,</hi> as the Apostle said, <hi>your Bodies are the Temple of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And also you may read <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2. the moderation and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> and his Queen to <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> though <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s Religion differed from theirs; and though he was a Heathen, he gave <hi>Nehemiah</hi> an Order to go and see <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi>'s Walls repaired, though he had much opposition by many bad people, and called rebellious, because they had not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served other Nations Religions, yet their persecuting came to naught, as you may see throughout <hi>Nehemiah:</hi> And so why should Christians be more unmercifull one to another, and persecute one another worse then the Heathen did the Jews? And so people are not to Hang,
<note place="margin">Ezra 7</note> Banish, Spoil Goods, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prison one another according to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the Heathen's Law, but to Love one another according to Christs Law, and Command; and so Priests have ignorantly brought this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Persecute, Banish, Imprison, and spoil Goods, who are darker then the Heathen, who gave Liberty to the Jews Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which was contrary to their own; and here the Priests
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204659:17"/>and Professors are ignorant of the Law and Times of the Gospel.</p>
               <p>And in the dayes of <hi>Ahasuerus</hi> King, <hi>Haman</hi> was set above all the Kings Princes, and all the Kings Servants bowed to <hi>Haman;</hi> and <hi>Mordecai</hi> sate in the Kings Gates, <hi>And the King gave command that they should bow to</hi> Haman; <hi>the Kings Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants which were in the Gate said to</hi> Mordecai, <hi>Why transgressest thou the Kings Command? and they spake daily unto</hi> Mordecai, <hi>and he hearkened not unto them: then the Servants told</hi> Haman, <hi>to see whether</hi> Mordecai'<hi>s matter would stand; for he had told them that he was a Jew; and when</hi> Haman <hi>saw that</hi> Mordecai <hi>did not bow, nor reverence him,</hi> Haman <hi>was full of wrath, and</hi> Haman <hi>scorned to lay hands on</hi> Mordecai <hi>alone, for they had shewed him the People of</hi> Mordecai, <hi>who was a Jew; wherefore</hi> Haman <hi>sought to destroy all the Jews throughout the whole Kingdom:</hi> Would not many of you Christians say that <hi>Mordecai</hi> was a Fool because he would not bow to <hi>Haman,</hi> and do according to the Custom of the Nation, but in denying to do such a small thing, to bring persecution and death upon himself and all the Jews; and so to be counted stubborn and rebellious, disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the Command of the King? And would you not say, let <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> Law go upon him, <hi>Whosoever will not obey the Law of God and the King, let judgment be speedily executed upon him, whether it be to death or banishment, or confiscation of goods or imprisoument,</hi> Ezra 7. Nay, <hi>Mordecai</hi> obeyed the Law of God, and was not rebellious, though he could not obey the Command of the King to bow to proud <hi>Haman;</hi> therefore <hi>Haman</hi> said to the King, <hi>There is a certain Poople scattered abroad among thy People, in all the Provinces in thy Kingdom, and their Lawes are divers from all People, neither keep they the Kings Laws; therefore it is not for the Kings profit to suffer them: If it please the King to let them be destroyed, I will pay Ten thousand Talents of Silver:</hi> and so <hi>Haman</hi> got a Decree from the King, and sent it forth to destroy the Jews. Now mind, here it is shewed, that the Jews had Liberty till this <hi>Haman</hi> got this Decree, because <hi>Mordecai</hi> the Jew would not bow to him, nor reverence him, though the Jews Religion differed from the Kings and <hi>Haman</hi>'s Religion: And <hi>Esther</hi> the Queen being a Jew, spoke to the King that the Jews were to be destroyed,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204659:18"/>who procured another Decree from the King, that the Jews should not be destroyed, which was sent into all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces. And <hi>Haman</hi> saw <hi>Mordecai</hi> sit in the Kings Gate, and stood not up, nor moved for him, <hi>Haman</hi> was full of fury, and therefore <hi>Haman</hi> caused a Gallows of fifty cubits high to be made to hang <hi>Mordecai</hi> on; and as <hi>Haman</hi> came back from the King he came back sorrowfull, for he was to clothe <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai,</hi> and set him on hors-back, and proclaim before him, and say, <hi>Thus shall be done to the man whom the King delighteth to honour:</hi> then <hi>Haman</hi> came home and told his Wife what had befaln him, and his Wife said, <hi>If</hi> Mordecai <hi>be of the seed of the Jews, before whom thou hast begun to fall, thou shalt not prevail, but fall;</hi> yet before <hi>Haman</hi>'s Wife and his Friends would have him set up a Gallows to hang <hi>Mordecai</hi> on, which he was hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on himself afterwards. Here you may see the end of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutor and Destroyer, who was against Liberty, and whether is there more <hi>Mordecais</hi> or <hi>Hamans</hi> in <hi>Christendom,</hi> that would kill and destroy men because they would not stand up and bow to them, and reverence them? Nay would they not say <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi> was an unmannerly ill-bred Clown? and would they not say he did it a purpose to lie in the Kings Gate, could he not keep out of the Kings Gate, for his doings was in danger to destroy all the Jews? and if <hi>Mordecai</hi> the outward Jew could not bow to proud <hi>Haman,</hi> though in so doing he did disobey the Kings Command, whether or no can the Jew inward in the Spirit bow to <hi>Haman</hi>'s nature where it appears? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Haman</hi>'s nature will not persecute though it be in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian? and should Christians be worse then the Jews, for Christians should not persecute one another for not bowing to one another? for the Angel in the <hi>Revelations</hi> reproved <hi>John</hi> for bowing to him, and told him he was his Fellow-Servant, and said, <hi>See thou do it not;</hi> and bid him <hi>Worship God, Rev.</hi> 22. So let <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s nature reign amongst you, and not <hi>Hamans,</hi> for mark <hi>Haman</hi>'s end; for the true Christians are Jews in the Spirit, and are Brethren; Christ says, <hi>You are all Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;</hi> for do not you, called Christians, call them impudent Clowns, and unmannerly that will not bow, and has fined ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and persecuted many? Is not this like <hi>Haman</hi>'s nature, not <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s?</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:204659:18"/>
               <p>And Christ, who has all power in Heaven and Earth given unto him, and to whom all Judgment is committed, he said, <hi>That for every idle word that men should speak, they should give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at the day of Judgment; so by thy words thou shalt be justified, and by thy words thou shalt be condemned,</hi> Mat. 12.20, 36, 37.</p>
               <p>And doth not Christ say in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Be thou reconciled to thy Brother before thou offer thy gift?</hi> Now if all Christians did observe this, who was there to offer amongst them; for such as envied their Brother Christian, and persecuted him, such were not to offer their gift until they were reconcil'd to the Brethren; for if they do God has no respect to their Sacrifice, no more then he has to <hi>Cain</hi>'s that envies his Brother: And Christ who hath all power in Heaven and Earth said, <hi>Judge not, lest you be judged; for with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged; and with what measure you meet, it shall be measured to you again:</hi> Now all you that are so rash in measuring, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and persecuting of others, you never think of this Law of Christ Jesus: Now it is clear that none are to judge till the Beam be cast out of their own eye, then they may see cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Moat, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. And doth not the Apostle say, <hi>That you must do good unto all men, &amp;c.</hi> which if you do good, you do not do evil: <hi>And every man must bear his burthen; and every man is to prove his own work; and every one shall give an account to God for things done in his Body, and shall have a reward according to his Works, whether they be good or whether they be evil; and every mans own words shall be his burthen: for God respects no mans person; for he that sowes to the flesh, shall of the flesh reap corruption; but he that sows to the Spirit, shall of the Spirit reap Life Everlasting;</hi> so every Seeds-man reaps his own crop, according to what he sows, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. the persecuting Priests and Professors used to bring for their Persecution; <hi>viz. I would they were cut off that trouble you;</hi> now this cutting off the Apostles troublers, it was with Spiritual weapons, for the Apostles warfare was not with Carnal, but with Spiritual Weapons; neither did he wrestle with Flesh and Blood, so that he could not cut them off with Carnal Weapons.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:204659:19"/>
               <p>And as the Apostle saith in <hi>Galatians</hi> 4. <hi>He that is boru after the Flesh will persecute him that is born after the Spirit; so it is now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Bond-woman and her Son must be cast out, and not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with the Free-woman:</hi> Now it is clear, it is the Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman and her Son that are cast our, that are the Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; so the persecuting Christian may know his Mother, for as it was in the dayes of <hi>Isaac,</hi> and in the dayes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, so it is now in these dayes, that the birth born after the Flesh will persecute him that is born after the Spirit, and these be the Children of the Bond-woman which genders to bondage, which is <hi>Hagar:</hi> but the Children of the Free-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man are of <hi>Isaac,</hi> in whom the Seed is called, and <hi>Jerusalem</hi> which is above is the Mother of all these Children which is Free, and gendreth not to Bondage, and are not Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors.</p>
               <p>And the Apostles command to the <hi>Collossians</hi> was, <hi>If ye be dead with Christ from the Rudiments of the World, why as living in the world are you subject to Ordinances; touch not, taste not, handle not, which all are to perish with the using, after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Doctrines of men.</hi> Now, [mark] Is there any Ordinances, Doctrines and Commandments of men, but they are held up by mens power? and will not they that are not dead with Christ taste, handle and touch, and be subject to them, and rage, and be envious, and persecute them that be dead with Christ, and cannot touch, taste nor handle, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be subject to them? So, is it not the birth of the Flesh that is subject to mens Doctrines, Ordinances and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which perish in the using of them, which they that be dead with Christ, and risen, seeks that which came down from above, from Christ who sits at the right hand of God; and so their affections are on things which are above, and after that which doth not perish, <hi>Colossians</hi> 2d and 3d chapters. And though the Apostle said to the <hi>Corinthians, If any man love not Jesus Christ, let him be an Athema and Maranatha,</hi> yet the Apostle plainly tells you, <hi>That they did not wrestle with Flesh and Blood, and the Weapons were Spiritual and not Carnal;</hi> and he tells you, <hi>That he that is born after the Flesh persecutes him
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204659:19"/>that is born after the Spirit,</hi> and the Spiritual Birth has his Spiritual Weapons, but the Carnal man has his Carnal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons; and so each Birth hath his Weapons.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Zachariah</hi> 13.3, 4. which is a place which the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting Priests and Professors used to bring for their Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; which is as followeth, <hi>I will cut off, saith the Lord, the names of the Idols out of the Land, and they shall be remembred no more; I will cause the Prophets and unclean Spirits to go out of the Land; And it shall come to pass, when any shall yet prophesie, then his Father and Mother which begat him shall say unto him, Thou shalt not live, for thou speakest Lyes in the Name of the Lord; and his Father and Mother shall thrust him through when he prophesies. In that day the Prophets shall be ashamed every one of his Vision when he hath prophesied; neither shall they wear a rough Garment to deceive.</hi> Now [mark] these Prophets with the rough Garment, which speaks Lyes in the Name of the Lord, with their unclean Spirits &amp; Idols, which were not to be suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Land among the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> but their Father and Mother was to run them through which begat them; but what must the Christians Weapons be now, that say they are not Jews outward, but they are Ministers of the Gospel, and believers in Christ? their Weapons must be all Spiritual, not Carnal, by which they run through the false Prophet, that false Spirit, and lying Spirit, and so their Weapons are Spiritual, they do not wrestle with Flesh and Blood. Are not these persecuting Priests and Professors in <hi>Christendom</hi> like unto these rough Prophets, that will serve for pay under any one, <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian, Papists</hi> or <hi>Piscopal,</hi> as the Souldiers used to serve under any one for pay, who wrestles with Flesh and Blood? And is it not their work to call to the Magistrate to help them to wrestle with Flesh and Blood, and them that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary minded to them? And are not these like the Prophets, that one while they would be for the Jews, and another while for <hi>Jezebel</hi> and <hi>Ahab;</hi> you may see how subject they were to turn, as you may read through the Scriptures; but the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apostles were not Persecutors, but persecuted: Was not <hi>Moses</hi> persecuted by <hi>Pharaoh?</hi> but what become of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204659:20"/>
                  <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and others that did persecute him? and was it not for Religion sake? Was no <hi>Abel</hi> murthered by <hi>Cain</hi> the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutor, about Religion? and though <hi>Cain</hi> could build Cities, yet was a Vagab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd; and doth not all Persecutors go in <hi>Cains</hi> way? read <hi>Jude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Children of <hi>Israel</hi> were oppressed under <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> mind the end of that Oppressor; and <hi>Elisha</hi> was persecuted by <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel,</hi> mind the Persecutors end: the Prophet <hi>Joath</hi> was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Jeroboam; Zachary</hi> was stoned to death for his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Was not <hi>Micah</hi> for his Religion thrown down, and his neck broken? Was not <hi>Amos</hi> smitten with a Club on the temples of his head, and so brained for his Religion sake? Was not <hi>Isaiah</hi> sawn asunder in two parts for his Religion? And was not <hi>Jeremiah</hi> for his Religion persecuted oft, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned, and put in a deep Dungeon, and after stoned to death in <hi>Egypt?</hi> Was not <hi>Ezekiel</hi> slain in <hi>Babylon,</hi> by the Duke of the People, for his Religion? And was not <hi>Daniel</hi> thrown into the Den of hungry Lions, where he was preserved? And was not the three Children thrown in the fiery Furnace for their Religion? And was not <hi>Baruch</hi> fain to fly to save his life from King <hi>Joash</hi>'s hand for his Religion, and Testimony? Was not the Prophet <hi>Ʋrias</hi> slain with the Sword by King <hi>Joaichim?</hi> Was not <hi>John Baptist</hi> beheaded by <hi>Herod</hi> the <hi>Tetrach?</hi> Was not <hi>Stephen</hi> stoned to death (by the great professing Jews) for his Religion? Was not <hi>James</hi> beheaded by <hi>Herod Agrippa?</hi> Was not <hi>Peter</hi> crucified at <hi>Rome</hi> under <hi>Nero,</hi> his head down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? Was not <hi>Andrew</hi> crucified by <hi>Aegeas</hi> King of <hi>Edissa</hi> at <hi>Pataras,</hi> a City in <hi>Achaia?</hi> Was not <hi>James Alpheus</hi> of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem</hi> thrown down from high, and brained with a Fullers Club? Was not <hi>Thomas</hi> slain at <hi>Calamina,</hi> a City in <hi>India,</hi> where the <hi>Panims</hi> ran him through with the Dart? Was not <hi>Philip</hi> crucified at <hi>Hyrapolis</hi> in <hi>Asia</hi> for his Religion? Was not <hi>Bartholomew</hi> fleid alive in <hi>Judea,</hi> and his skin pluckt over his Ears, and after beheaded? Was not <hi>Martha</hi> run through with a naked sword in <hi>Ethiopia?</hi> Was not <hi>Simon</hi> crucified? Was not <hi>Jude</hi> slain; and <hi>John</hi> scourged, and often times perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and put in scalding hot Oyl? Was not <hi>Matthias</hi> knockt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204659:20"/>on the head with an Ax, and beheaded? Was not <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangelist a rope put about his neck, and by it drawn through the City of <hi>Alexandria</hi> till his flesh rent in pieces, and the stones coloured with his Blood, and at last was burnt to ashes? Had not <hi>Barnabas</hi> a Rope tyed about his neck, and there pluckt to the stake and burned? [Mark] Did not all these suffer for Religion, and that that persecuted them, was it not the Birth that is born of the Flesh; and is not this Birth now to be seen in <hi>Christendom</hi> which doth persecute him that is born of the Spirit, wrestling with Flesh and Blood: and so what is become of all these Persecutors; doth not the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the Wicked rot, and the memorial of the Just live?</p>
               <p>Was not <hi>Jacob</hi> persecuted by <hi>Esau</hi> because of his Blessing <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.41. And was not <hi>Joseph</hi> persecuted by his Brethren, who after banisht him, and sold him; and was it not for that which God had shewed unto <hi>Joseph,</hi> which after came to pass; and had his Brethren any praise for this work; were they not afterwards troubled and judged in themselves for the same? And was not <hi>Lot</hi> persecuted and mockt in <hi>Sodom;</hi> read what became of those temporal blind <hi>Sodomites</hi> persecuting (then you may say what will become of these Spiritual blind perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting <hi>Sodomites</hi>) of the Just. And if outward <hi>Sodom</hi> was consumed to ashes, what will become of the Spiritual <hi>Sodom;</hi> and was not persecution alwayes blind?</p>
               <p>And did not Christ say, that the persecuting Priest and Pharisees were <hi>Blind-Guides, and led the Blind into the Ditch;</hi> and are not all the Persecuting Priests and Teachers now in <hi>Christendom</hi> Blind-guides; and will any be led by them but the Blind, is not the place they lead into the Ditch, and is not the persecution against them that can see: and so all the Guides in Christendom that persecute, are they not the Blind ones, and doing the works of the night, not of the day, wherein people can see: and is not the Brith which persecutes, that which was born bind from <hi>Hagars</hi> womb, and not born of the womb of the true woman which <hi>Isaac</hi> came of; for <hi>Hagar</hi> was an Egyptian woman that bore wild <hi>Ishmael, whose hand is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204659:21"/>against every man:</hi> So now, Is not the spirit of <hi>Cain,</hi> and the spirit of <hi>Core,</hi> and the Spirit of <hi>Sodom</hi> to be seen, and of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and of the persecuting Jews; and doth not the spirit of all these reign in him that is born of the Flesh?</p>
               <p>Had not <hi>Abraham,</hi> that came out of his own Country, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to serve God among the <hi>Canaanites;</hi> and when <hi>Abraham</hi> went down into <hi>Egypt,</hi> had he not liberty there to serve God, as you may read in <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. though the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites</hi> were bad people: And had not <hi>Abraham</hi> liberty to serve God in the <hi>Abimelecks</hi> Country; and <hi>Abimelech</hi> said, <hi>My Land is before thee, dwell where it pleaseth thee:</hi> And in what Country was there a Law made, that <hi>Abraham, Isaac,</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> should not worship and serve the God of Heaven,
<note place="margin">Gen 20.</note> though they differed from the Countries Religion; and though the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> were opprest in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where do you ever read that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> made a Law that <hi>Joseph</hi> nor the People of <hi>Israel</hi> should not serve the Lord their God whilst they were among them, though when they multiplied another King op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed them with hard labour, and gave a command to hinder their growth, to kill all the male children, but the Midwives fearing God did not as the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> had commanded them, to kill all the men children: now would not many in <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> say, that these Midwives were rebellious to the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and that <hi>Artazerxes</hi> Law should be executed upon them, of death and banishment, for disobeying the Kings Law; for if the Pope, or others should make a Law, that they should burn, kill, banish and imprison would not you be willing, though it be contrary to your Consciences to obey it, contrary to the Command of Christ Jesus, that you should love one another, and not destroy one another, and you doing so, <hi>viz.</hi> obeying the Papists or others Commands to destroy people that fears God; doth not the Midwives that feared God judge you, (who disobeyed the Command of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi>) in not destroying the childrens lives? <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.14. When <hi>Saul</hi> the King gave command that <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> his Son should die, for tasting of the Honey which <hi>Saul</hi> had forbidden that any man should eat any food that day, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204659:21"/>therefore his Son which had tasted a little Honey might die: And the people disobeyed the Command of <hi>Saul,</hi> and said, <hi>Jonathan should not die, for he had wrought Salvation in Israel;</hi> so rash Oathes and Commands them that feared God you may see could not obey.</p>
               <p>Another Scripture which the Priests and Papists used to bring to put men to death about Religion is <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. <hi>The man that will do presumtuously, and will not hearken to the Priest that standeth to minister before the Lord, or unto the Judge, that man shall die.</hi> Now [mark] people, this is one of the Scriptures that Papists used to bring, because they would not hear their Priests; so mark their ignorance, for do not you know that these were the Jews Levitical Priests; and then must not all Papists, Protestants, and others be put to death if they will not hear the Jews Priests that was to minister the Law. But I say Christ is come, that saves mens lives, and came not to destroy them, which ends the Jews Priests, and the Law by which they were made, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. and their Carnal Weapons; and so Christ, who is the Priest made higher then the Heavens, is to be heard in all things, and not the Jewish Priests, as you may read in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. &amp; <hi>Acts</hi> 7. And another Scripture they bring, <hi>The Prophet that shall presume to speak a word in my Name, which I have not commanded him to speak, or that shall speak in the name of other gods, then the Prophet shall die.</hi> Now [mark] did ever you Papists, or others called Priests or Prophets, ever hear the voice of God, which you have all denied to us, called Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, that ever you did; then is not this Sentence faln upon your selves, as dead men, according to your own Judgement; but this is your ignorance, Christ is come the great Prophet, which ends the true Prophets, who is to be heard, and is the Stone which falls upon the false spiritual Prophets, that has not heard the voice of God, and stones them to death, and yet saves the mens lives: and Christ ends the Jews Carnal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and sets up the Spiritual, by which they do not wrestle with Flesh and Blood, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>And also in <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. another Scripture the Papists and Protestants used to bring for Persecution, <hi>If there rise up any
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204659:22"/>Prophet or Dreamer, or give thee a sign and wonder, and the sign or wonder come to pass whereof he speaks to thee saying, Let us go after other gods, and serve them, and so to forsake the Lord God, and his Commandments, that Prophet or Dreamer shall be put to death; If thy Brother the Son of thy Mother, or the Son of thy Daughter, or thy wife, or thy Friend of thy own Soul shall in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret entice thee to serve other gods, thou shalt not consent to them, neither pitty them, nor spare them, nor conceal them, thou shalt kill him, and thy hand shall be first upon him to put him to death, and shall stone him with stones that he die, because he sought to turn you from the Lord God.</hi> And now [mark] people these were them that by their Dreams and Prophesies would bring people from the Living God, to serve other Gods, which were by the Jews Law to be stoned to death, though they were their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, as before mentioned; but Christ is come, who has ended the Jews Law, and their Weapons, and their Religion and Worship, and has set up the Gospel, the worship in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Truth; and Christ did not give forth any Law, nor his Disciples after him did not give forth any Law to put men to death, though they were false Worshippers; for you see many did forsake Christ that had followed him, and many did forsake the Apostles which had been convinced, and drawed others after them; yet neither Christ nor the Apostles did make a Law that such should be put to death; for Christ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked his Disciples who would have had mens lives destroyed, and said, <hi>He came to save them, not to destroy them;</hi> and his Commandment was, <hi>That they should love one another, and love Enemies;</hi> and Christ is the Top and Corner-Stone which falls upon the false Dreamers, and false Prophets, and stones them to death, yet saves the men And you may read in <hi>Jude,</hi> and in <hi>Peter,</hi> there was filthy Dreamers in their dayes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> yet the Apostles did not make a Law to put them to death, though they drawed people from the power of Christ; for the Apostle tells you, his Weapons are Spiritual, and not Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, they do not wrestle with Plesh and Blood, nor war with it, but with spiritual wickednesses, and it was the spiritual wickednesses in them that made them false Prophets and false
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204659:22"/>Dreamers to draw People from God, and that the Apostles warred against with Spiritual Weapons, and did not war with Flesh and Blood, and stone the Creatures to death; that Law of the Jews is Changed by Christ that puts men to death about Religion, and Christ has set up his Law of Love, to love one another, and love Enemies, and though Christ was called a Blasphemer, a Seducer, a Devil, and a Madman, yet he did not make a Law to put them to death, and stone them to death; and did not he pray to his Father to forgive them that persecuted him; but you Papists, and others, if it should be granted to you, that Prophets and Dreamers that draws People from the Living God and his Commands to serve other Gods, and you that would have the Jews Law which you bring out of <hi>Ezra</hi> past upon them Christians; then doth not the Jews Law come upon your selves? for after you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated Bread and Wine, do you not say it is God, and so by the Jews Law are not you to be put to death, who set up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God, and draws people to it, and so are condemned out of your own Scriptures? though I say Christ has ended the Law and their Weapons, and the Jews Religion, <hi>And he is not a Jew that is one outward, but he is a Jew that is one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the Spirit,</hi> as in <hi>Romans.</hi> But if you Papists should say that they must be put to death that draws from Christ and his Command, then I say, as I said before, you have given sentence upon your selves by your own Law, which you had not from Christ, for Christ's Law is, <hi>Love one another, and love Enemies;</hi> and so from this Law and Command have you erred, and by it you are judged, who have instead of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one another, you have envied, persecuted and killed one another, like <hi>Cain,</hi> and so are of him that is of the Flesh, that persecutes him that is born of the Spirit, who are neither according to the Law of Jesus among the true Christians, nor the Law among the Jews; for that birth of the Flesh in you is that which alwayes did persecute them that gave forth the Scriptures, and Christ the Substance of them, and them that live the Life of them: and so that birth of the Flesh is that which did not give forth the Scriptures, neither doth know them, nor can interpret them; and so a Command from God
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204659:23"/>is, <hi>That Flesh must be silent,</hi> and so the Birth of the Flesh must be silent, that will persecute him that is born after the Spirit; and so he that is born of the Spirit he must speak, whose Weapons are not Carnal, neither doth wrestle with Flesh and Blood, nor war with it; <hi>Christendom</hi> mind this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joshua</hi> 9. <hi>Joshua</hi> let the <hi>Gibbonites</hi> have liberty, who got it by craft, though his Command from God was to destroy all the wicked people of the Land; and though they were wicked people, and they got it by subtilty, yet he let them have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and surely Christians should be beyond <hi>Joshua,</hi> not to restrain those from liberty who desired nothing but liberty to worship God; for the <hi>Gibbonites</hi> did not seek for their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to worship God; and therefore there should be a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt Christians that seeks for no liberty but to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God, and the <hi>Gibbonites;</hi> for the Christians all profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth Christ Jesus and God, so did not the <hi>Gibbonites,</hi> and they are not to make one another Slaves, as you may see in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations</hi> 18 <hi>Which made Merchandise of the Souls of men, and Slaves of them,</hi> this you will say was the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> that made Merchandise; and you know it is judged by all the Protestants that the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> is such as profess Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity, and to be the Papists, and such as are in the same Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and you know this is contrary to the primitive Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Law, which is, <hi>To love one another, and Enemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, universal Pope, was set up by <hi>Phocus</hi> that murthered <hi>Mauritius,</hi> his Master, which was the first uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Pope got up, Six hundred and two years after Christ, and about twenty years after the Turk got up; and has not the Christians siberty under the Turk, paying their Tribute, and not meddled with for their Religion? for, doth not the Turk keep his Sabbath day upon the Sixth day, and then his Shops are shut up, and all the Shops of the Jews and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> open? and doth not the Jews keep their Sabbath upon the Seven the day in <hi>Turkey,</hi> and then all the Christians and Turks Shops are open? And the Christians they keep their Sabbath upon the First day of the week, and shuts up their shops, and all Turks and Jews shops are open. And here doth not the Turk give Liberty of Conscience, though he be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204659:23"/>a Heathen; and should not Christians outstrip the Turk, and give liberty to one another to worship God? And hath not the <hi>Corinthians</hi> liberty in <hi>Turkey,</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to worship God, and follow their own Religion? And is not this doing of the Turks beyond Christians that cannot give liberty to one another? And do not you know that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians have their liberty in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> though it be in the Turks Country, and though they differ from his Religion? And when the Turk conquors any Country, doth not he let the people alone to their Religion, so he can have his Tribute and Custom? And also when <hi>Alexander</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the World, did not he let the Jews have their Liberty? And when the <hi>Romans</hi> conquered <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> had not the Jews liberty, read the Scriptures? In the dayes of Christ and the Apostles was there not many Sects, as of Pharisees and Sadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among the Jews at that day, as you may read in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? and had not they liberty among the Jews, though dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered from one another in circumstance? And is there not in the <hi>Mogull</hi>'s Country many sorts of Religion? Yea, and has not some Christians liberty there to serve God, of whom it is reported by one that travelled there, he has sixty Religions there that has their liberty without disturbance, paying their Customs? And should not Christians be of a more nobler spirit then he? Has not the Christians liberty in <hi>Persia?</hi> and among the Turks, is there not a many kinds of Religions amongst them, that differ in some thing? and should not Christians be of a more noble Spirit, and give liberty to one another to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God, though they differ in some outward things, seeing they all own God and Christ Jesus? and therefore should not they be of a more nobler spirit then the Turk, Mogull, and the Persians? and hath not the Arrians and Pope been the two first that raised Persecution, one Christian against another, contrary to the Law of Christ, Love Enemies, and love one another? and so has not Christ's Law of Love been laid aside?</p>
               <p>And after that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> transgressed the Law of God, God let <hi>Adam</hi> have liberty in the Earth, though he had not of the Paradice of God; and so though Christians cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204659:24"/>to your Church in tenderness of Conscience towards God, you may let them have liberty of the Earth; and though <hi>Ishmael</hi> the wild man had not liberty in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, he had liberty in the Wilderness.</p>
               <p>And concerning the Act that is made against the Quakers, and others; as for us that are called Quakers, this we say, we do not meet to plot nor contrive against the King, neither do we hold dangerous Principles, but the Truth; neither do we meet to terrifie the Kings Subjects, but seek the good and eternal welfare of the King, and all people; and we do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor and detest all Plots and Plotters and Workers of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: And whereas the same Act prohibits above five to meet together, had you been in the dayes of Christ and the Apostles, this Act would have taken hold upon him; for you know he had twelve Apostles, and seventy Disciples, who often met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And also it would have taken hold upon the <hi>Ephesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Philippians</hi> and <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and all the other Churches that did meet together: And do you think that they would not have suffered either by Heathen or Christians, before they would have broke up their Meetings, or Christ have denied his Disciples? If some Christians, or Heathen that differed from them should have made a Law, that those Christians that differed from them should not meet above five at a time; and is not, and would not that have been contrary to Jesus, who said, <hi>Love one another, and Enemies,</hi> who has all power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth given unto him; for do you ever read that Christ and the Apostles made a Law to punish, or to make any one suffer that did not hear them, or differed from them in Religion and Worship? And did you ever read that the Jews made any Law that not passing five might meet of the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, though the Christians Religion was contrary to theirs? And so seeing that God will judge the World in Righteousness, sign fying that there is something in man and woman which answers the Righteousness which they do transgress; and he will judge the World by the Man Christ Jesus, according to the Gospel, that is according to the Power, shewing, that there is something in man that answers the Power which is the Gospel, and is invisible; and they that walk in the Power
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204659:24"/>which is the Gospel, they ought to have the liberty of the Gospel, which is the Power of God, before the Devil was, where all Bondage is; and so all Christians that owns God and Christ Jesus, and his Gospel which is the Power of God before the Devil was, they ought to have the liberty of the Gospel, for the liberty is in the Power of God, and they that be in the Power of God, the Gospel cannot but give liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to them that be in the Power of God, for the bondage is in that spirit that is out of the Power of God, and the Liberty is in Christ Jesus who has all power in Heaven and Earth given unto him, and there <hi>to stand fast in the Liberty wherewith Christ hath set them free from the bondage of the World;</hi> shewing, that it is the World that brings into bondage, and not Christ.</p>
               <p>They that wrestle with Flesh and Blood about Religion, are neither in the Apostles Spirit, nor Power, nor Doctrine, and if the Law reach but upon the outward man for his action, then it will follow, and is clear, that the inward man after God must have his Liberty, which inward man brings the outward man conformable to the righteousness, and to a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous mans state, which the outward Law was not made for, so then it is not to be executed upon the righteous man: So all Magistrates must make a distinction, and put a difference in this case; for though Kings powers, and Magistrates with their Laws take hold upon the outward evil actions, and the outward man the evil spirit leading of him to do evil; but Christ who is the King of Kings, and has all power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, he must have the rule in the heart of the Spiritual Man, <hi>and God will dwell in man, and walk in man, which is his Temple,</hi> and therefore he must have the rule in the Conscience, and in the Heart in matters of his Religion, and Worship, and Faith, seeing God is the giver of it, and Christ is the Author and finisher of it; and the Apostles themselves said, <hi>they had not power over mens Faith,</hi> which God was the giver of, and Christ the finisher of; and a man coming to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due that evil spirit in him by the Power of God, and to have it mortified, and the actions that flowed from it, then the man led by the Spirit of God, he is not under the Law which is made for Sinners and Disobedient, and not for the Righteous;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204659:25"/>And Christ said, <hi>Christians should not exercise lordship one over another as the Gentiles had done;</hi> and the Apostle says, <hi>Be not many Masters, for you have one Master, even Christ, and they were not lords over Gods Heritage, but they were helpers of their joy, and thoy should not lord it over their Brethren, for they were all Brethren;</hi> and this he spoke in matters of Religion, <hi>for they had one Lord, even Christ Jesus, by whom all things was made, and one God who is over all, and in you all blessed for ever:</hi> and so if Christ be in you, and God be in you, he must have the rule in matters of Religion; for his Religion is pure from above, from himself, he must have the Rule of the Faith, who is the Author of it, and Christ must have the Rule of his Worship, who set it up above Sixteen hundred years since, in Spirit and Truth: For could the <hi>Caldeans</hi> find any thing against <hi>Daniel,</hi> save in the matters of his God; and could you ever find any thing against the Quakers, but concerning their God, and the worship of him? Could <hi>Cain</hi> find any thing against <hi>Abel,</hi> but the matters of his God; or <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Sons against <hi>Joseph,</hi> but concerning his God? or could any fault be found with <hi>Isaiah, Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Elisha</hi> in their dayes, but that which concerned their God? or could they find any fault with Christ or the Apostles, for which they persecuted them, but only things concerning their God and Christ? and ever since the Apostles dayes the Beast, the Whore, the false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and Antichrist, which has drunk the Blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, Prophets and Saints who have kept the Testimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, was not all this persecution upon them concerning their God the Christ Jesus? for what fault could they find in them more then they did in <hi>Daniel</hi> concerning his God? And so you may read through all the Scriptures of <hi>Abraham, Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the rest of the Prophets, <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> did not their sufferings come upon them concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their God? for what fault could they find with them? or what fault could <hi>Pharaoh</hi> find with <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> but of things concerning their God? or <hi>Sodom</hi> with <hi>Lot,</hi> or the old World with <hi>Noah,</hi> but in things concerning their God? and so its clear all along the birth of the Flesh has alwayes persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the birth of the Spirit, as it is written, <hi>He that is born of the Flesh persecutes him that is born of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:204659:25"/>
               <p>And Christ Jesus who set up his Worship above Sixteen hundred years since, who said, <hi>The hour is come, and now is, they that worships the Father must worship him in Spirit and Truth, such God seeks to worship him;</hi> and Christ and the Apostles never altered this worship to this day, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship was set up before the many worships among Christians were set up, and will stand when they are gone; and Christ is the Judge in this worship set up by himself, and not by man; and Christ gave no Law, nor Command, or order to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles to persecute any that did not worship according to his Worship, which you may see all the worship set up by men, one time or other most of them has forced people to their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and persecuted for not conforming, and that forcing makes but Hypocrites from their worship to anothers; and mark the end of all those worships and Worshippers in the World where there has been force and persecution, that which men makes and sets up they are judge of, and judge in, and is not this to bring people to worship the works of mens hands? and the Worship that Christ set up he is the Judge of, which is in the Spirit and Truth.</p>
               <p>And so it is plain it is <hi>Cain</hi> is the first birth that has persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Abel</hi> the second birth in all Ages; and this <hi>Gain</hi> the first birth, and persecutor of <hi>Abel,</hi> God hath not, nor never had respect unto his Sacrifice who is <hi>Cain</hi>'s Off-spring, the first birth, and not of <hi>Abels:</hi> and so <hi>Cain</hi> may read his Birth and Antiquity, and suffering <hi>Abel</hi> may read his Birth and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, whom God had and hath respect unto his Sacrifice. Yet had not <hi>Paul</hi> liberty at <hi>Rome</hi> among the Heathen <hi>Romans</hi> that were of a different Religion from <hi>Paul,</hi> to preach the Gospel two years together in his own hired house, as you may see in the <hi>Acts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Law was added because of Transgression, and not made for the Righteous, but for Sinners and disobedient: [mark] because of Transgression and Disobedience was the Law add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; man and woman in the beginning disobeyed and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed the Command of God, and so lost the Image of God and his Righteousness, and the Paradice of God; and so the Law which is just, holy and good came upon disobedient and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:204659:26"/>transgressing man and woman, which Law served until the Seed came, and Christ is the end of Law for righteousness sake the to every one that believeth.</p>
               <p>And seeing that because of Transgression the Law was add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then they that do not transgress, the Law doth not take hold on, neither are they under it.</p>
               <p>And seeing the Law was made for the disobedient and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, then he that doth not disobey Gods Command, but is led by the Spirit of God, is not under the Law.</p>
               <p>And they that keep Gods Commandments, and do not transgress, are not under the Law; and therefore must not Magistrates make a distinction, and put a difference betwixt the Transgressors and Disobedient, and the Obedient and them that doth not transgress.</p>
               <p>And now Christians, Papists and others, what say you to the Apostles that disobeyed the Command of the Councel of the Jews, in preaching again in the Name of Jesus after they had commanded they should not preach, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. would not you say that <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> Law was to be executed upon them, and they to be imprisonned, banished, and put to death, or their goods confiscated? And also would not you have said, that this Law of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> was justly to have been executed upon <hi>Daniel</hi> and the three Children for disobeying the Kings Command? Would not you say that it should be executed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Midwives for not executing <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Command in killing the men children, who has brought this Law to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted upon Christians?</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his Heathens Law and Gods Law which was for the Jews to build the Temple, you that call your selves Christians, are you Jews? and are you going to build the Jews Temple, which Law was before Christ came in the Flesh? for except you go to fulfil <hi>Artaxerxe</hi>'s Law, and to build the Temple, <hi>Artaxerxe</hi>'s Law is against you; for no ones goods is to be spoil'd, or any to be banished, imprisoned, or put to death for not going to build the Temple of the Jews at out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Jerusalem</hi> now; <hi>For he is not a Jew that is one outward;</hi> for the Jews Temple is ended by Christ, and the Law which held up the Jews Religion, Temple and Priest; for by the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:204659:26"/>Jews Law you never read that any were to be put to death, or banisht, and goods spoiled for not repairing or building the Temple at outward <hi>Jerusalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Jerusalem</hi> that is now, that is below, is in bondage with her Children by the Turk, as she was under the Romans Power in the Apostles dayes: But <hi>Jerusalem</hi> that is above is free, and is to be free in her Religion, Faith, Worship and Gospel, who is the Mother of us all the true Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, which has a new Command from Christ, which is not to banish, kill, put to death, spoil goods, but <hi>to love one another,</hi> and this is the Law of Jesus who has all power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven given unto him, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; and so his Command is to be observed, and he is to be heard i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all things, and not <hi>Artaxerxe</hi>'s Law, <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. nor the Jews, not <hi>Ezra</hi> the Priest with his Law to build the Jews Temple.</p>
               <p>And the Apostle in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. speaks of such that be without natural affections; as such as are without natural affections, as has not affections to Nature, but will destroy, prison and persecute the workmanship of Gods hands, and Gods Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures he has created, about their worships and their Religion; and such as are without natural affections are such as can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be appeased, nor be mercifull, but merciless, and such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroys the good nature in themselves, by which they have not natural affections to their natural brethren; for <hi>Cain</hi> destroyed the natural affections in himself before he destroyed his natural brother; for Nature is one, and would not destroy it self, and it hath affections to it self; but the Serpent going out of Truth, leading man and woman from the Truth, so corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and destroying nature in themselves, by which they are led by an evil spirit to destroy nature without them, and have not affections to it, and this has been the work of the Enemy, and all the Killers and Persecuters about Religion and Worship in the whole World to this day; for they that destroys nature about such things cannot have affection to nature, but are without natural affections, and they that are without natural affections cannot know the Divine things given forth by the holy men of God, Christ, and the Apostles from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:204659:27"/>to the ending of the Scriptures; and they that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out natural affections cannot love the Brotherhood, nor love one another, nor Enemies, therefore such do not keep the Command of Christ; and therefore they that do love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and love Enemies has affections to nature, and would not have one another destroyed which are Gods Creatures, and so loves all things which God made, whose works praise him; and such have not only natural affections to Nature, but the Divine Nature, and the affections set upon things which are above, so they have affections to things of nature, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to things above; so as the Apostle says, <hi>He that says he loves God and hates his brother is a Lyar;</hi> so all that say they love God (in <hi>Christendom</hi>) what follows, what are they? what says the Apostle, <hi>He is a Lyar that hates his Brethren; for how can he love God which he hath not seen, and hate his brother which he hath seen;</hi> so mark this sound reason, <hi>Whosoever hateth his Brother is a man-slayer, and ye know that no man-slayer hath Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life abiding in him;</hi> so take notice of this great Apostles words all <hi>Christendom,</hi> you that hates your Brethren, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutes them, the great Apostle says, and tells you, <hi>You are Man slayers, and have not Eternal Life abiding in you,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. <hi>And he that hateth his Brother is in darkness until this time, and he that loveth his Brother abideth in the Light;</hi> and mark, Christendom, <hi>He that hateth his Brother is in darkness, and walketh in darkness, and knoweth not whither he goeth, because that darkness hath blinded his eyes:</hi> So now consider this all ye that do hate your Brethren what the Apople says, your path is not in Light, but in Darkness, and you do not know whither you go, but Darkness hath blinded your eyes; and therefore lay away hatred, that your eyes may be opened, that you may come out of Darkness, and walk in the Light, that you may keep the Command of Christ, which is, <hi>To love one another, and Enemies,</hi> and that you may come out of Darkness, and know whether you go. And so, Is it not clear, that they whose eyes are blinded, who walks in Darkness hating their Brethren, is not this hatred come from the Serpent, who was the first hater,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:204659:27"/>who hated <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eves</hi> prosperity and dominion over all things God made? Is not this Darkness they walk in that hate their Brethren from the Prince of Darkness, the Serpent? And is it not he that has blinded their eyes, who are hoodwink'd with the Serpents hatred and darkness, that they do not know whither they go, which they that walk in the Light, and love the Brethren, know whither they go, and in them there is no occasion of stumbling? And how can they which hate their Brethren, and walk in the Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness which has blinded their eyes know the Scriptures, which holy men spoke as moved of the holy Ghost? And has it not been the work of them that walks in Darkness to hate and persecute such? And has not the original been from the Serpent, and not from God and Christ which says, <hi>Love one another, and Enemies?</hi> And this is in love to you all for your Eternal good.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>G F.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>